the services that satellites provide us, the satellites themselves deserve our attention as they are leaving a lasting mark on the space they occupy. People around the world rely on satellite infrastructure every day for information, entertainment and to communicate. There's agricultural and environmental monitoring, Internet connectivity, navigation. Satellites even play a role in the operation of our financial and energy markets. But these satellites that we rely on day in and day out have a finite life. They might run out of propellant, they could malfunction, or they may just naturally reach the end of their mission life. At this point, these satellites effectively become space junk, cluttering the orbital environment. So imagine you're driving down the highway on a beautiful, sunny day out running errands. You've got your music cranked, your windows rolled down, with the cool breeze blowing through your hair. Feels nice, right? Everything is going smoothly until suddenly your car stutters and stalls right in the middle of the highway. So now you have no choice but to abandon your car where it is on the highway. Maybe you were lucky enough to be able to move it out of the way and into a shoulder lane so that it's out of the way of other traffic. A couple of hours ago, your car was a useful machine that you relied on in your everyday life.
los servicios que nos proveen los satélites, estos requieren de nuestra atención ya que dejan una marca imborrable en el espacio que ocupan. En todo el mundo, la gente depende de la infraestructura satelital en todo momento sea para buscar información, entretenerse o comunicarse. Existe incluso un monitoreo en la agricultura, en el medioambiente en la conexión y navegación web. Los satélites tienen gran importancia en el funcionamiento de los mercados financieros y energéticos. Sin embargo, estos satélites en los que confiamos día a día, tienen una fecha de caducidad. Pueden quedarse sin combustible, presentar fallas, o simplemente llegar al fin de su vida útil. Si fuera así, estos satélites se convierten en chatarra espacial, abarrotando el entorno de la órbita. Imaginen que conducen por la autopista en un hermoso día soleado haciendo toda clase de mandados. Con la música a todo volumen, las ventanillas bajas, la fresca brisa que agita el cabello. Suena bien, ¿verdad? Todo parece estar tranquilo, hasta que, de repente, su auto se sacude y se detiene justo en medio de la carretera. No hay otra opción que dejar el auto en donde está. Tal vez si tuvieron suerte lograron dejarlo fuera del camino, en una cuneta para que no interfiera con el tránsito. Hasta hace un par de horas, el auto era una máquina útil en la que confiaban a diario.
Now, it's a useless hunk of metal taking up space in a valuable transportation network. And imagine international roadways all cluttered with broken down vehicles that are just getting in the way of other traffic.
Ahora es una pieza de metal inútil que ocupa espacio en una red de transporte vital. Imaginen rutas internacionales abarrotadas de vehículos sin funcionar que solo ocupan lugar en el tránsito.
And imagine the debris that would be strewn everywhere if a collision actually happened, thousands of smaller pieces of debris becoming new obstacles. This is the paradigm of the satellite industry. Satellites that are no longer working are often left to deorbit over many, many years, or only moved out of the way as a temporary solution. And there are no international laws in space to enforce us to clean up after ourselves. So the world's first satellite, Sputnik I, was launched in 1957, and in that year, there were only a total of three launch attempts. Decades later and dozens of countries from all around the world have launched thousands of more satellites into orbit, and the frequency of launches is only going to increase in the future, especially if you consider things like the possibility of 900-plus satellite constellations being launched. Now, we send satellites to different orbits depending on what they're needed for. One of the most common places we send satellites is the low Earth orbit, possibly to image the surface of Earth at up to about 2,000 kilometers altitude. Satellites there are naturally buffeted by Earth's atmosphere, so their orbits naturally decay, and they'll eventually burn up, probably within a couple of decades. Another common place we send satellites is the geostationary orbit at about 35,000 kilometers altitude. Satellites there remain in the same place above Earth as the Earth rotates, which enables things like communications or television broadcast, for example. Satellites in high orbits like these could remain there for centuries. And then there's the orbit coined "the graveyard," the ominous junk or disposal orbits, where some satellites are intentionally placed at the end of their life so that they're out of the way of common operational orbits. Of the nearly 7,000 satellites launched since the late 1950s, only about one in seven is currently operational, and in addition to the satellites that are no longer working, there's also hundreds of thousands of marble-sized debris and millions of paint chip-sized debris that are also orbiting around the Earth. Space debris is a major risk to space missions, but also to the satellites that we rely on each and every day. Now, because space debris and junk has become increasingly worrisome, there have been some national and international efforts to develop technical standards to help us limit the generation of additional debris. So for example, there are recommendations for those low-Earth orbiting spacecraft to be made to deorbit in under 25 years, but that's still a really long time, especially if a satellite hasn't been working for years. There's also mandates for those dead geostationary spacecraft to be moved into a graveyard orbit. But neither of these guidelines is binding under international law, and the understanding is that they will be implemented through national mechanisms. These guidelines are also not long-term, they're not proactive, nor do they address the debris that's already up there. They're only in place to limit the future creation of debris. Space junk is no one's responsibility. Now, Mount Everest is actually an interesting comparison of a new approach to how we interact with our environments, as it's often given the dubious honor of being the world's highest garbage dump. Decades after the first conquest of the world's highest peak, tons of rubbish left behind by climbers has started to raise concern, and you may have read in the news that there's speculation that Nepal will crack down on mountaineers with stricter enforcement of penalties and legal obligations. The goal, of course, is to persuade climbers to clean up after themselves, so maybe local not-for-profits will pay climbers who bring down extra waste, or expeditions might organize voluntary cleanup trips. And yet still many climbers feel that independent groups should police themselves. There's no simple or easy answer, and even well-intentioned efforts at conservation often run into problems. But that doesn't mean we shouldn't do everything in our power to protect the environments that we rely and depend on, and like Everest, the remote location and inadequate infrastructure of the orbital environment make waste disposal a challenging problem. But we simply cannot reach new heights and create an even higher garbage dump, one that's out of this world. The reality of space is that if a component on a satellite breaks down, there really are limited opportunities for repairs, and only at great cost. But what if we were smarter about how we designed satellites? What if all satellites, regardless of what country they were built in, had to be standardized in some way for recycling, servicing or active deorbiting? What if there actually were international laws with teeth that enforced end-of-life disposal of satellites instead of moving them out of the way as a temporary solution? Or maybe satellite manufacturers need to be charged a deposit to even launch a satellite into orbit, and that deposit would only be returned if the satellite was disposed of properly or if they cleaned up some quota of debris. Or maybe a satellite needs to have technology on board to help accelerate deorbit. There are some encouraging signs.
Imaginen los restos desparramados por todas partes, si un accidente realmente ocurriera, miles de pequeños restos formarían nuevos obstáculos. Este es el paradigma de la industria satelital; por lo general los satélites que ya no funcionan son abandonados en las órbitas durante varios años, o simplemente se mueven del camino como una solución temporal. Y no existen leyes internacionales en el espacio que nos obliguen a retirar esos restos. El primer satélite del mundo, el Sputnik I, fue lanzado en 1957 y en ese mismo año hubo tres intentos de lanzamientos. Décadas más tarde, cientos de países han lanzado miles de satélites a órbita, y la frecuencia de los lanzamientos cada vez es más alta, en especial si se consideran aspectos como la probabilidad del lanzamiento de más de 900 satélites en constelaciones. En la actualidad, lanzamos satélites a diversas órbitas dependiendo en cual sea su uso. Uno de los lugares más habituales adonde se envían los satélites es a la parte baja de la órbita terrestre, probablemente por sobre la superficie terrestre a hasta una altitud de unos 2000 km. Los satélites se ven perjudicados por la atmósfera terrestre, es por eso que es habitual que sus órbitas decaigan y eventualmente se desintegren, probablemente en unas cuantas décadas. Otro lugar habitual adonde enviamos a los satélites es a la órbita geoestacionaria, que yace a una altitud de unos 35 000 km. Allí permanecen en el mismo lugar sobre la tierra mientras que esta gira, lo que permite servicios de comunicación, o emisión televisiva. Los satélites en órbitas lejanas podrían permanecer allí por siglos. Y luego existe "la órbita cementerio", las órbitas de desechado o de chatarra abandonada donde se colocan algunos satélites al finalizar su vida útil para que permanezcan alejados de las órbitas en funcionamiento. De los 7.000 satélites lanzados desde fines de los años 50 solo 1 de cada 7 funcionan actualmente y, además de los satélites que ya no funcionan, también permanecen miles y millones de pequeños y grandes escombros que también orbitan alrededor de la Tierra. La chatarra espacial presenta alto riesgo para las misiones espaciales, pero también para los satélites de los que dependemos. Hoy, debido a que la chatarra espacial es un asunto apremiante, se han realizado intentos tanto a nivel nacional como internacional de desarrollar regulaciones técnicas para limitar la cantidad de escombro adicional. Por ejemplo, existen sugerencias para las naves que recorren la órbita baja para que no permanezcan allí más de 25 años pero aún ello es mucho tiempo, en especial si un satélite ha dejado de funcionar en años. También existen regulaciones para aquellas naves geoestacionarias para que se trasladen a una órbita cementerio. Pero ninguna de estas pautas responde a la legislación internacional y se supone que cada país debe implementar sus normas. Estas pautas tampoco son a largo plazo, no son proactivas tampoco abarcan a la chatarra que ya está acumulada. Simplemente se limitan a la futura formación de escombros. Nadie se responsabiliza por la chatarra espacial. El monte Everest es una interesante comparación de un nuevo enfoque de cómo interactuamos con el ambiente y muchas veces se le acusa de ser el montículo de basura más grande del mundo. Luego de la conquista del pico más alto del mundo, los escaladores dejaron toneladas de basura que han comenzado a generar preocupación y en los medios se especula que en Nepal se tomaran medidas contra los montañistas mediante regulaciones y sanciones estrictas. Esto es para incentivar a los escaladores a recoger sus propios residuos, es por ello que tal vez se recompense a aquellos que contribuyan, o se organicen viajes para recolectar residuos de forma voluntaria. Y aún así varios sentirán que las asociaciones independientes deberían regular por sí mismas. No hay una solución simple e incluso los bienintencionados esfuerzos para conservar muchas veces dan más problemas. Pero ello no significa que no se deba hacer todo para proteger al medioambiente del que dependemos y, como el Everest, la infraestructura inadecuada y remota de la órbita espacial hace que el deshecho de basura represente un gran problema. Pero no podemos crear montañas de basura cada vez más grandes, incluso fuera de este planeta. La realidad en el espacio es que si una pieza de un satélite se rompe, son pocas las probabilidades de repararla y representa un gran costo. Pero, ¿qué tal si diseñáramos mejores satélites? ¿Qué tal si todos los satélites, independientemente del país que los construya, deban seguir un estándar para su reciclaje, servicio, o incluso sacarlos de órbita? ¿Qué tal si existieran regulaciones internacionales que obliguen a desechar los satélites en lugar de quitarlos del camino como una solución temporal? O quizás se le deba cobrar un depósito a los fabricantes de satélites para lanzarlos al espacio y este solo se devolvería si los satélites fueran desechados correctamente o si retiraran los restos que producen. O tal vez que posean la tecnología necesaria para lograr que salieran de órbita rápidamente. Hay indicios alentadores.
The UK's TechDemoSat-1, launched in 2014, for example, was designed for end-of-life disposal via a small drag sail. This works for the satellite because it's small, but satellites that are higher or in larger orbits or are larger altogether, like the size of school buses, will require other disposal options. So maybe you get into things like high-powered lasers or tugging using nets or tethers, as crazy as those sound in the short term. And then one really cool possibility is the idea of orbital tow trucks or space mechanics. Imagine if a robotic arm on some sort of space tow truck could fix the broken components on a satellite, making them usable again. Or what if that very same robotic arm could refuel the propellant tank on a spacecraft that relies on chemical propulsion just like you or I would refuel the fuel tanks on our cars? Robotic repair and maintenance could extend the lives of hundreds of satellites orbiting around the Earth. Whatever the disposal or cleanup options we come up with, it's clearly not just a technical problem. There's also complex space laws and politics that we have to sort out. Simply put, we haven't found a way to use space sustainably yet. Exploring, innovating to change the way we live and work are what we as humans do, and in space exploration, we're literally moving beyond the boundaries of Earth. But as we push thresholds in the name of learning and innovation, we must remember that accountability for our environments never goes away. There is without doubt congestion in the low Earth and geostationary orbits, and we cannot keep launching new satellites to replace the ones that have broken down without doing something about them first, just like we would never leave a broken down car in the middle of the highway. Next time you use your phone, check the weather or use your GPS, think about the satellite technologies that make those activities possible. But also think about the very impact that the satellites have on the environment surrounding Earth, and help spread the message that together we must reduce our impact. Earth orbit is breathtakingly beautiful and our gateway to exploration. It's up to us to keep it that way. Thank you. (Applause)
Por ejemplo, el TechDemoSat-1, que el Reino Unido lanzó en 2014, fue diseñado para desecharse al finalizar su vida útil mediante un pequeño mecanismo de anclaje. Esto funciona porque no ocupa lugar, pero los satélites o sus órbitas ocupan más lugar ya que juntos o por separado son de gran tamaño y requerirán de otros métodos alternativos. Tal vez se lleguen a crear cosas como láseres de largo alcance o mecanismos de arraste mediante redes o nudos, aunque suenen descabellados en el corto plazo. Y una interesante posibilidad es la de grúas o mecánicos espaciales. Imagina que un brazo robótico en alguna especie de grúa espacial pueda reparar las piezas de un satélite haciéndolo útil otra vez. O si ese mismo brazo robótico pueda recargar el tanque de combustible de las naves que dependan de propulsión química así como lo hacemos aquí, con nuestros automóviles. La reparación y mantenimiento robotizados podrían extender la vida útil de cientos de satélites que orbitan la Tierra. Es obvio que este problema no se reduce a un problema técnico. Existen leyes espaciales y políticas muy complejas que debemos conocer. Hemos usado el espacio de forma poco sustentable. Explorando, innovando, para cambiar nuestras vidas es lo que hemos hecho, y en la exploración espacial nos movemos más allá de los límites terrestres. Pero al atravesar esos límites, debemos tener en cuenta a nuestro medioambiente. Hay acumulación de satélites en la baja órbita terrestre y en la geoestacionaria y no podemos seguir lanzando satélites para reemplazar a aquellos que se rompieron sin intentar repararlos primero así como no lo haríamos con un automóvil roto en el medio de la carretera. La próxima vez que uses tu teléfono móvil, revises el clima o usen el GPS, recuerden a la tecnología satelital que lo hace posible. Pero también recuerden el impacto que tienen los satélites en el medio ambiente y que depende de nosotros reducir el impacto. La órbita terrestre es asombrosamente hermosa y nuestra puerta para explorar el espacio. De nosotros depende mantenerla así. Gracias. (Aplausos)